<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some ways for raising of money humbly offer'd to the consideration of the Parliament / by a person of quality.</title>
            <author>Person of quality.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60874</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4633</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11597</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11910560</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11910560</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50802</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60874)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50802)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 514:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some ways for raising of money humbly offer'd to the consideration of the Parliament / by a person of quality.</title>
                  <author>Person of quality.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by Randall Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Taxation --  England.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1649-1775.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50802:1"/>
            <p>SOME WAYS FOR <hi>Raiſing of Money,</hi> Humbly offer'd to the Conſideration of the PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>BY A Perſon of Quality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Randall Taylor</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50802:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50802:2"/>
            <head>Some Ways for <hi>Raiſing of Money,</hi> Humbly offered to the Conſideration of the Parliament.</head>
            <p>THE beſt way of all others is an Exciſe; under which Head the following Particulars (or moſt of them) will be reduced. This Way will be the moſt effectual to raiſe great Sums of Money, and will be the leaſt felt: And it is uſed by all wiſe and civiliz'd Nations, who find it the beſt and eaſieſt way. But tho it were not ſo, yet now in this great Exigence, and when all lies at ſtake, and ſuch mighty Sums are wanting to preſerve us, we ſhould not be afraid of it. It is not here meant, that we ſhould have a general Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe upon all things bought and ſold (for that ſeems too troubleſom and vexatious); but only upon ſome things of general uſe, and which can well bear the Duty. I ſhall name ſome few of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Farthing a Pound upon all <hi>Fleſh</hi> ſold by retail, the Offals excepted with effectual proviſion, that no Fleſh ſhall be ſold in Towns, ſave only in the Market, or in the Shops or Shambles.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An Halfpenny a Pound upon all <hi>Candles</hi> ſold. Theſe two eaſie Duties would clear ſix hundred thouſand Pounds a Year.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Sixth part of the Value, or Two Pence in the Shilling upon all <hi>Paper</hi> imported; but ſo as none to pay
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50802:3"/>above One Shilling the Ream. This would give a mighty Advantage to our new Manufacture of Paper in <hi>England;</hi> which therefore might well afford to pay the half of this Duty, or the Twelfth part of the Value.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Sealed Paper</hi> and <hi>Parchment</hi> for Bonds, Contracts, and Conveyances, without which, no Writing which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the Seal of the Parties, to be good and valid. Tho this Duty were made light, yet it would bring in great Sums, and would be very eaſily gathered. As it is found by Experience in other Countries.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When the <hi>Aſſize of Bread</hi> is above Ten Ounces for the Penny White Loaf; the Exceſs, or what is over and above, to be a Duty to the King, and the Bread to be made at Ten Ounces.</p>
            <p n="6">6. An additional Duty of Twelve Pound <hi>per</hi> Tonne at the leaſt, upon <hi>French Wine;</hi> and this to be inſtead of the Prohibition. It would keep it out much more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually: For now, though it be prohibited, it is as plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful as ever. And as leſs would come in than does now; ſo that which comes in under ſuch Duties, would advance great Sums towards our publick Occaſions, yielding very ſmall and miſerable Gains to the <hi>French</hi> Seller.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Six Pound <hi>per</hi> Tonne addition upon all <hi>other Wines;</hi> which they may well afford to pay, the <hi>French</hi> paying ſo much more. Nor can our Friends take it ill, if in this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xigence we encreaſe the Duty upon their Wines, ſince we double it upon our own Beer and Ale. Alſo by this means, <hi>French</hi> Wines, which are chiefly aim'd at, could not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape, by pretending them to be from other places; for all Wines would now have near the ſame Burthen. And ſince at the <hi>Canaries</hi> they are grown ſo rich and ſo proud, that they will not now take our Woollen Manufactures, nor ſcarce any thing elſe we have, ſo that we muſt carry Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or give them Bills to <hi>Spain;</hi> therefore there ſhould
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50802:3"/>be a further Addition of Duty upon their Wines: for nothing will bring them down, but a Company or high Duties.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Two or three Shillings <hi>per</hi> Gallon upon all <hi>Brandy</hi> imported; and <hi>French Brandy</hi> to pay double; and their Double Brandy to pay double to that.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Forty or Fifty <hi>per Cent.</hi> Addition upon <hi>all other French Commodities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe few things would bring in more Money than our great Land-Tax of an Hundred Thirty Seven Thouſand Pounds a Month. And theſe might be for continuance, if occaſion ſhould require. I have now two Ways to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, which will only advance a preſent Sum, and are not for continuance.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, a <hi>Review of the Taxes of One Shilling and Three Shillings in the Pound.</hi> Theſe Taxes were the moſt equal of all others, had they been well aſſeſs'd; but they were aſſeſs'd ſo ſhamefully ill, that thereby the Taxes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the moſt unequal. Some Lands were aſſeſs'd at the full value, ſome hardly at half, and ſome not at all. I heard a Gentleman of <hi>Surrey</hi> affirm, That he knew of Three Thouſand Pounds a Year in his Neighbourhood, which paid not a Penny to thoſe Taxes. It is therefore humbly propoſed, that a Review be in this manner. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners to be named by the King for each County, and chang'd at pleaſure. The major part to be of the ſame County. Theſe to ſit every Month, or oftener if occaſion be, to receive and hear Informations of Eſtates under rated, and to determine them according to their Conſciences. What ſhall come in by this Way, to go half to the King, and half to the Informer. (for except the Informer be well rewarded, there is no good to be done in things of this kind) Before any Information be received, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50802:4"/>to ſit once or twice, to receive the Confeſſions of the Parties themſelves; who by this means may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Informer. They that confeſs the true Value, to ſave the one half of what they were under-rated, paying the other half to the King. No Information to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved after Three Years. It is verily believed, that His Majeſties ſhare of this Gleaning will come to Three or Four Hundred Thouſand Pounds. And here will be an equal Aſſeſſment for the future, ſuch as never was in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Way here offered is, <hi>A Compoſition for the Iriſh Eſtates.</hi> Which may be thus. That all King <hi>James</hi> his Adherents in that Kingdom, who ſhall come in by ſuch a time, be pardon'd and have their Lands, paying Two Years purchaſe of their true Value, as it was Three Years ago. ſome few of the moſt notorious and miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous being excepted. To incline us to go by this Way of Compoſition, rather than by Confiſcation and Sale, let us conſider the matters here following.</p>
            <p>Firſt let us conſider, that it is the more merciful, and conſequently the more Chriſtian Way. Whereas, if we ſhould Confiſcate all theſe Eſtates, and turn the People a begging, together with their Wives and Children; it would be the ſevereſt Victory that hath been known a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians. Would it not ſeem extremely rigorous, if we ſhould put them all to the Sword? And the ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping them of their Eſtates is as bad or worſe. It were a Mercy to take away their Lives, rather than leave them in ſo great Miſery. This <hi>French</hi> King hath lately ſubdued <hi>Savoy:</hi> but we do not hear of any Confiſcations or Extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations; nor are their Lands made a Prey to the conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Army, but every Man enjoys his own. The ſame <hi>French</hi> King, when he had ſetled his Conqueſts in <hi>Flanders,</hi> gave publick notice to the Gentlemen of thoſe Countries,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50802:4"/>who were in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Service, that if they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn home by a time prefixed, and become his Subjects, they ſhould have their Eſtates. They asked the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s permiſſion, who granted it: And thereupon, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken ſolemn leave of their Friends at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home and had their Eſtates. It cannot be denyed, but that this was an Action truly noble of all ſides. That we may look farther back; it was one of the chief Glories of <hi>Richelieu's</hi> Adminiſtration, that when his King had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Rochel,</hi> and entirely ſubdu'd the Proteſtants; he not only pardon'd them their Lives and Eſtates, but likewiſe continu'd to them their Religious Liberties, without any Diminution. We muſt not be aſhamed to take Example by our Enemies, in what they do well; rather we ſhould ſtrive to exceed them.</p>
            <p>Secondly let us conſider, that theſe Peoples Crime is not ſo horrible as ſome would ſuppoſe it. King <hi>James</hi> plainly forſook the Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> but that of <hi>Ireland</hi> he did not ſeem to forſake. He retain'd the Government there, firſt by his Lieutenant, and then in perſon. And who can think it unpardonable, if theſe People adher'd to their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral King; being alſo of their own Religion, and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Friend and Patron? If we will be impartial, we can hardly blame them for what they have done. Beſide, though they had ſuch ſtrong Motives, yet they were hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevail'd upon to engage and declare. They knew there were ſome Men in the World, that had a great mind to their Lands; and they were very loth to hazard them. But being left to themſelves for many Months, and to the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices and Perſuaſions of King <hi>James</hi> his Agents; and no Power but King <hi>James</hi>'s appearing in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and we in <hi>England</hi> being wholly taken up with ſetling our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; they were drawn in to do that, which perhaps wiſer Men than they would have done in their Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:50802:5"/>
Let us thirdly conſider, That theſe are the antient Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants and Proprietors of that Country: That they are our Country-men at large: and have been our Fellow-Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects for ſome Hundreds of Years. Though many of them be rude and wild, yet they are as we found them; and in time they may be reclaimed. How many civil Proteſtant Families are there already in <hi>Ireland,</hi> of mere <hi>Iriſh</hi> Extraction?</p>
            <p>We ſhould conſider in the fourth place, That Mens not ſubmitting to a new-eſtabliſh'd Government, is not ſo hainous a Crime, as the Rebelling againſt a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they were born under, or to which they have ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Who can think it ſtrange, if there be ſome Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences and Diſorders, upon a Diſſolution of Government? And in ſuch a Caſe, muſt nothing leſs than Deſtruction be thought a ſufficient Puniſhment? Suppoſe a part of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in a great Revolution, ſhould not readily conform with the reſt; muſt they for this be utterly deſtroy'd and extirpated? Or, which is the ſame thing, muſt their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates be made a Prey, and themſelves made miſerable Beggars? This would ſeem to us, eſpecially to thoſe of us that felt it, very hard and ſevere. And let us not deceive our ſelves in our own partial Imaginations. There is as much Mercy, in ſuch a Caſe, due to <hi>Iriſh</hi>-Men, as there is to Us <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly we may conſider, That the way of Clemency here propoſed, will be near as beneficial to us, as the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Severity. eſpecially if we reckon how much it will ſave. In all humane probability it will put a ſudden end to the War, and ſave the further effuſion of Blood and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Since the Victory at the <hi>Boyne,</hi> we have been fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>Iriſh</hi> Lands; which, I doubt, hath coſt us more al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, than thoſe Lands are worth. Let us throw away no more upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50802:5"/>
Sixthly we muſt conſider, That we have an Enemy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, who is ready to ſwallow up all <hi>Europe.</hi> Any one may know, that I mean the <hi>French</hi> King. Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take heed, leſt by being too obſtinately bent to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> we be deſtroy'd our ſelves by the <hi>French.</hi> There is now a mighty Confederacy againſt this <hi>French</hi> King. but they have two great Diverſions; namely the War againſt the <hi>Turk,</hi> and this of <hi>Ireland.</hi> The Emperor was much overſeen, in not making Peace with the <hi>Turk</hi> laſt Winter: which Peace they that diſſuaded and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, did thereby great Service to the <hi>French.</hi> and we ſhould take care not to fall into the like Error; by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing the War of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Which may have ſo fatal a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, as the Ruine of all <hi>Europe,</hi> and of our ſelves among the reſt. 'Tis a Voyage Royal into <hi>France,</hi> that muſt ſupport both Us and our Confederates. and therefore it concerns us to unite all our Forces, for a Voyage Royal into <hi>France.</hi> which I pray God to proſper.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we ſhould do well to conſider, what are the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and Sentiments of our Friends, and likewiſe of our Enemies, in this <hi>Iriſh</hi> Affair. It cannot be doubted, but that it is the paſſionate Deſire of our Friends and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, that we would make up with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> upon any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Terms: that ſo we might aſſail the <hi>French</hi> with all the Force we can make. Which how greatly it would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage our Confederates, is eaſie to imagine. On the other ſide, it muſt be the Wiſh of our great Enemy the <hi>French</hi> King, that we would give the <hi>Iriſh</hi> no Terms, but proſecute them with the utmoſt Rigour. That thereby they may be obliged and enforced to continue the War, and to defend themſelves to the laſt Extremity. And that Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the mean time may beat us out of the Sea, may over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear our Confederates at Land, and even invade <hi>England</hi> it ſelf. When we conſider theſe things, I hope we ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50802:6"/>deavour to fulfil the Deſire of our Friends, and ſhall not do as our Enemies would have us.</p>
            <p>There are ſome Objections againſt this Deſign of Mercy to the poor <hi>Iriſh;</hi> to which ſome Anſwer muſt be given.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is ſaid (to make their Crime ſeem greater), <hi>That</hi> Ireland <hi>is a ſubordinate Kingdom to</hi> England: <hi>and muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore comply with whatever we do.</hi> I anſwer, That this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence cannot hold in all Caſes. For if <hi>England,</hi> ſhould be invaded and ſubdued by a forraine Enemy (which God avert), and ſhould be forced to ſubmit to the Conquerour; it would not follow, that the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> when they might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves, muſt ſubmit to the forraine Yoke like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. What we did in the late Revolution, was done up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Grounds ſo righteous, as may juſtify us to all the World. But put the caſe, that we <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men ſhould without any pretence or colour throw oft our lawful Prince: would the <hi>Iriſh</hi> be obliged in duty to do the ſame? Or to make the thing ſhorter; If <hi>England</hi> rebell, muſt <hi>Ireland</hi> rebell to? and if they will not do it readily, muſt they be rooted out?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The</hi> Iriſh <hi>will never be quiet.</hi> I anſwer, They muſt be quiet, ſince they will not be in condition to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. From the time the Long Parliament ſubdued them, they have been very meek and tame. Yet I confeſs, that when we had ſet up Popiſh Kings in <hi>England,</hi> who gave all Countenance and Authority to the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and at laſt put Arms into their hands and diſarmed the Proteſtants; the Proteſtant Engliſh Intereſt was in danger. which yet had never been run down, had they had any aſſiſtance from <hi>England</hi> in time, and had they not ſuffer'd themſelves to be fool'd by <hi>Tirconnell.</hi> But there can be no danger to the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> unleſs we ſet up Popiſh Kings in <hi>England.</hi> which I ſuppoſe we ſhall never do.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:50802:6"/>
3. <hi>We cannot live with Comfort intermixt with the</hi> Iriſh-Truly then we muſt come away from them, and leave them in their Country by themſelves. But ſhall We who have thruſt our ſelves in amongſt Them, now not ſuffer Them to live amongſt Us? This were too inſolent, and void of all Humanity.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Our Army muſt be rewarded out of theſe Lands.</hi> But why muſt Our Army, more than all others, think to be thus rewarded? There is no other Army we know of, that expects any ſuch thing. Beſide, they may have their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards as well out of the Compoſitions, as out of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcations.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>They called in the</hi> French: <hi>which is never to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given.</hi> But I deny that they called in the <hi>French.</hi> 'Tis true, they received King <hi>James;</hi> and then King <hi>James</hi> brought in the <hi>French:</hi> but without the conſent of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and againſt their Wills. But moreover, why ſhould it be ſuch a capital unpardonable Crime, to make uſe of forrain Aid? Why ſhould that be made a Crime in the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> which all People do for their own preſervation?</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>There was a full pardon once granted to the</hi> Iriſh; <hi>which they did not accept, nor come in upon it.</hi> But I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that this was while our King was here in <hi>England,</hi> and far from them: and when King <hi>James</hi> was in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and amongſt them, and in Power. So that we muſt not blame them too much, if they did not or durſt not then comply, with the gracious Offers that were. made them. But after the Victory at the <hi>Boyne,</hi> had a full Pardon been granted, or Conditions offered that had been tolerable; there is little reaſon to doubt, but that they had readily ſubmitted: King <hi>James</hi> himſelf giving them leave, when he fled from them. And then we might have had an Army in <hi>France,</hi> before the end of Summer. Alſo if we had profeſſedly been kind to the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> in honor and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50802:7"/>for the ſake of our Roman Catholick Allies, it had been a high Complement. But if after that glorious Victory, none were to be pardoned, ſave Labourers and common Soldiers and the like; and they that had any thing, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially all they that had Lands, <hi>were left to the Event of War;</hi> if all that theſe could hope for, was only to ſave their Lives, and be ſtripped of their Eſtates, and thrown into Miſery and Beggery; who can wonder if Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came obſtinate, that had been made deſperate? But by this means, while We fight to get their Eſtates, and They fight to keep them; the devouring War continues: all our Forces are employed upon <hi>Ireland:</hi> our Allies in the mean time are run down by the <hi>French,</hi> and brought to the brink of Ruine: and we in <hi>England</hi> lie under Taxes, ſuch as never were known. I ſpeak of theſe things with the greater freedome, becauſe I do well know, that our ſevere Reſolutions (the Cauſe of all) were carried, againſt his Majeſties merciful Inclinations.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>They have a perfect Averſion and Hatred to the</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh <hi>Government, and will never ſubmit.</hi> In anſwer to this, it muſt be confeſt; that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> may not much delight in their Subjection to <hi>England.</hi> and to ſpeak impartially, there is ſome reaſon for it. To ſee the <hi>Engliſh</hi> crowd into their Country, who are continually growing upon them and eating them out; who have alſo all the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Preferments, while themſelves are contemptible Underlings; it may well be, that theſe things are not very pleaſing to them. Nor ſhould We Engliſhmen be content to be ſo ſerved, by the <hi>French</hi> or any other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It muſt not therefore ſeem ſtrange, if theſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would willingly recover their antient and native Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; and ſhall act by the Principles of ſelf-Preſervation, as other men do. But for all their impatience of the Yoke, yet doubtleſs they will ſubmit, to prevent a ruine. They
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50802:7"/>would ſubmit to the <hi>Turk,</hi> when there is no remedy, thereby to ſave their Eſtates. and ſo would any Men elſe. We may well preſume, that the <hi>French</hi> Domination is odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the <hi>Savoyards:</hi> But yet we ſee they ſubmit to it. But why are the Landed Men of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſuppoſed more obſtinate than others? And why are not they pardon'd as well as others? I doubt the World will think, that we are too much ſet upon the Prey, and that the Love of their Land makes us ſo ſevere to them. And the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nobility and Gentry, who are the Men chiefly concern'd, will ſeem to be purſued (like the Hunted <hi>Caſtor</hi>) rather for what they have, than for what they have done. It will be little honour to our Nation;, to be thought (I will not ſay Beaſts of Prey, but) more intent upon the Prey than other People. Even this <hi>French</hi> King, though he hath been cruel and inhumane to his poor Proteſtant Subjects, yet he hath not made a Prey of them, but hath ſuffer'd and order'd their Eſtates to go to the next a kin, that are or will turn Papiſts. Laſtly, if they will not ſubmit when fair Terms are offer'd; they may then thank themſelves for their deſtruction, and We have done what becowes us. But in Juſtice, they ſhould have ſome Terms offer'd them, and in Prudence (conſidering our Circumſtances) ſuch termes as they will accept. What we thus get out of them, tho' it be far leſs then hath been propoſed, will be clear Gains.</p>
            <p>Thus I have endeavoured to demonſtrate, that, both in Prudence and Juſtice, the poor <hi>Iriſh</hi> ought to be well uſed at this time. And that the admitting them to a fair Compoſition, is one of the beſt ways of raiſing Money<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the finding out whereof, or at leaſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50802:8"/>the offering ſomething towards it, is the Scope and Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Paper.</p>
            <p>IT hath been humbly propoſed in the foregoing Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe that high Duties be laid upon <hi>French</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>modities, inſtead of the Prohibition. By which means much fewer of them would come in, then do now, and thoſe that did come in would be uſeful to the Publique, by yielding and raiſing great Summes of Money. I ſhall now endeavour to make theſe things more plain: eſpecially the former. for the latter ſeems evident of it ſelfe. I ſay then, that high Duties upon theſe Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties would more effectually clog and hinder their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation, then thier being wholly prohibited. And the reaſon is, becauſe the Duties cannot be ſo eaſily eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as the Prohibition (by Experience) hath been, and alwaies will be. The Officers of the Cuſtomes make it their buſineſs to collect the Duties to the King's utmoſt Profit. and they are in great meaſure Judges in the caſe. But to make out a forfeiture of prohibited Goods, there muſt be an Action at Law, and the thing muſt be tryed by Jury. who will expect clear legal Proofs, which perhaps cannot be had. So that though the Officer know the Goods to be <hi>French,</hi> and could demand and receive a Duty accordingly, in caſe a Duty were impoſed; yet he will not ſeize them as forfeited, and engage in a Law-Suit, unleſs he be ſure that he can ſatisfy a Jury. And even at beſt, a Law-Suit is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome. We ſee therefore that though the prohibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Goods be the ſeverer way, yet being the more difficult in the Execution, 'tis the leſt effectual.</p>
            <p>Moreover that high Duties are effectual to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, we find by a late Example. Since this War, as I
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50802:8"/>am well inform'd, the People of <hi>Devonſhire</hi> and <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall</hi> found meanes to ſend over good Quantities of Tinne and Lead, and ſome other things into <hi>France.</hi> But the <hi>French</hi> King quickly took care to lay ſuch Duties upon them, as hath at once put an end to that Trade. Which was alſo the <hi>French</hi> way before the War. they ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the vending of our Commodities there, not by prohibiting, but by impoſing high Duties.</p>
            <p>There hath been a Reaſon omitted, why the Laws for prohibiting Goods are ſlackly executed: which Reaſon is this. To ſeize ſuch Goods, and purſue them to a forfeiture, is to be the immediate Miniſter of inflicting puniſhments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Offenders. Which is an ugly Employment, not unlike that of the Hangman. So that good men do not care to meddle with it. The Officers therefore of the Cuſtoms, in whoſe way theſe matters lie, are apt to connive at ſuch Goods; and to allow of any pretence or colour for them, rather then turn Informers. But the ſame Officers will not-fail to collect the Kings Duties to the height: and to uſe their utmoſt care and diligence, that he be not defrauded.</p>
            <p>We ſee therefore, that it is much eaſier to avoid Forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and elude Prohibitions, then to eſcape high Duties. and Duties may be made ſuch a Burden, as the Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties cannot bear: and then no body will bring them.</p>
            <p>I have now ſomething more to ſay in particular, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>French</hi> Wines. If we can pinch them cloſe in their Wines, we gain a great point. But the preſent Prohibition will not do. For great Quantities are ſtill brought in, partly bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, and partly under other Names. But a high Duty would be ſure to meet with them. It hath therefore been here humbly offered, that beſide the twelve pound a Tonne which is the preſent Duty, there be laid upon them twelve pound more at the leaſt. At one word, the Addition (if it be thought fit) may be eighteen pound; making Thirty
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50802:9"/>pound in the whole. And if any do come in upon thoſe termes, the harm is not great.</p>
            <p>They will endeavour to evade this great Duty, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending their Wines to be from other Places. But if they are plain French Wines, the Officers of the Cuſtomes will not be impoſed upon: and will collect the Duty (as they ought) to the Kings beſt advantage. But the difficulty will be, in caſe they mix them with other Wines. And we are told, that they have already ſet up a trade of brewing and diſguiſing Wines, both in <hi>Portugal</hi> and more eſpecially in <hi>Zealand.</hi> To which places great quantities of <hi>French</hi> Wines are carried, and from thence (with a ſmall mixture or tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of other Wines) they are ſent to <hi>England.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to make ſure, and to prevent all ſhifts, it hath been further propoſed, that there be an increaſe of Duty upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Wines alſo. that is, ſix pound a Tonne upon the Wines of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> and upon the <hi>Rheniſh</hi> (which go by another meaſure) in proportion. ſo that the whole Duty of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Portugal</hi> Wines would be about four and twenty pound a Tonne. And ſo much <hi>French</hi> Wines muſt pay; tho' they be ſo diſguiſed as to paſs for other Wines, notwithſtanding the Officers Care. But if any part be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged <hi>French,</hi> the Wine to pay <hi>French</hi> Duties. This ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Duty the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Wines might well bear, as it hath been noted already, in regard the <hi>French</hi> have three times as much added. For the <hi>French</hi> Wines being in a manner ſhut out by the high Duty; the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> though their Duties be increaſed, will come in upon better ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage then ever they did formerly. But by this means, conſiderable Summs will be advanced for our publick Services, which is the thing aimed at in this whole Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
